<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The oyle of gladnesse. Or, Comfort for dejected sinners First preached in the parish church of Banbury in certaine sermons, and now published in this present treatise. By William Whately minister there.</title>
            <author>Whately, William, 1583-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836566</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15010)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1191:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The oyle of gladnesse. Or, Comfort for dejected sinners First preached in the parish church of Banbury in certaine sermons, and now published in this present treatise. By William Whately minister there.</title>
                  <author>Whately, William, 1583-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 199, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. M[iller] for George Edwards, and are to be sold at his house in Greene-Arbour, at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:847:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:847:1"/>
            <p>THE OYLE <hi>OF</hi> GLADNESSE. <hi>OR,</hi> Comfort for dejected ſinners. Firſt preached in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Banbury</hi> in certaine Sermons , And now publiſhed in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Treatiſe. <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM WHATELY Miniſter there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G M.</hi> for <hi>George Edwards,</hi> and are to he ſold at his houſe in Greene-Arbour, at the ſigne of the Angell 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:847:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:847:2"/>
            <head>To all wearied ſinners, all happineſſe here and hereafter bee granted, and this following Treatiſe be dedicated.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved in our LORD. You know it was one part of <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſts office,<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.4 &amp; Luk. 3.5.</note> to fill valleys, as was foretold of him. Valleys are dejected ſinners, filling the valleys, is, comforting of ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. This Worke is both
<pb facs="tcp:847:3"/>neceſſary and difficult. For to what purpoſe is it to beate downe a ſinner, if he be not raiſed up againe? The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhing of an old houſe doth not affoord habitation, if a new building be not ſet up in its roome: ſo neither doth the casting downe of mens high thoughts, make them a fit dwelling for God; if the faire pallace of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort be not alſo erected in them. Our ſoules are not united to God in hearty love, nor ſubjected to him in ſincere obedience, by bare terrors: (nay, that bitter anguiſh, which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the ſight of ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:847:3"/>and death deſerved by ſin, will rather increaſe our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity against God, and irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate our rebellious nature, if it be not ſomewhat ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by hope.) It is the ſweetneſſe of God (the taſte whereof affordeth more content in him, then any thing could give, which would allure us from him) that makes the heart to cleave to him, and to his waies. Worldly buſineſſes, are better diſpatched, after Sunne-riſing, then at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; ſo men doe make beſt ſpeede in a journey, by day-light: ſo doth the journey of a godly conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,
<pb facs="tcp:847:4"/>and the whole work of righteouſneſſe, goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward moſt proſperouſly, when the ſhining beames of ſpirituall gladneſſe, have inlightened the ſoule, as it were a quiet and light morning after a darke and tempeſtuous night. How hard a thing it is to quiet the troubled ſoule, they can beſt tell, that have beene moſt imployed in it. The divell oppoſeth the ſucceſſe of that labour with all his might, and craft; for hee findeth inexperience, that the Lord hath none ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and valiant ſouldiers, in all his army as thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:847:4"/>whom he hath first deepely wounded and after ſoundly healed. Terrors are the ſores of the very conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the tenderest part of the whole ſoule, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not eaſily cured. Carnall reaſon, the falſe guide of man-kinde, doth alwaies follow ſence, which in this caſe, doth miniſter nothing but appearing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, of never bing comforted, and a world of labour it will prove to withdrawe a man from following this guide. The truth is, none can rebuke theſe waves and ſtormes, (ſaying to them peace and
<pb facs="tcp:847:5"/>be ſtill, that a great calme may follow) but alone our Lord Ieſus Chriſt whom even the windes and the ſeas do obey. Yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaias</hi> telleth us,<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.19</note> that God createth the fruit of the lips to be peace peace. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, exhortations, directions, comfortable ſpee-&amp; perſwaſions of the godly, cheefely the Miniſters of the Goſpell, that ſtand in Chriſts ſtead, theſe be the fruit of the lips, theſe are the meanes by which the Lord doth ſtabliſh the ſoules of his ſervants in aſſured quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at last. I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to contribute
<pb facs="tcp:847:5"/>ſomething, to the cheering up of ſpirituall weepers, in this Treatiſe. This I offer to you burdened ſoules; as for others, I know how little agreement ſuch foode hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with their pallates. But before you reade, what I have here written and publiſhed, take with you an advertiſement or two. The principall hinderances of comfort, are unfitneſſe for it, and averſeneſſe from it. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſſe ſprings either from want of ſincerity, in ones not being ready to ſee and acknowledge ſome ſinne or ſinnes, which God would have him ſee, but he hangs
<pb facs="tcp:847:6"/>backe: or elſe from want of humility in that a man doth not bring his heart, to ſtoope ſo low to Gods juſtice, as to yeeld himſelfe into his hand without murmuring or quarreling. Till God have wrought us to his own bent (as it were) in theſe two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, there is no hope of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; Make haste therfore to let the Lord have his will in theſe two points. Now averſeneſſe from comfort, is a kinde of ſpirituall pettiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or peeviſhneſſe (which was ſometimes in the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 77.2.</note> who ſaith, <hi>My ſoule refuſed comfort</hi>) which makes men love to ſtrive
<pb facs="tcp:847:6"/>againſt their owne peace, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king great paines to thruſt comfort away from them, &amp; giving over themſelves, either ſtill to renew the old or multiply new objections againſt themſelves, to ſtudy to have ſomething to ſay againſt all that may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for them, never conſidering, nor obſerving how true and reaſonable the things are, which be ſpoken on their owne behalfe. The divell, (a great wranglex, that labours ſtill to darken truths of this kinde and not to cleere them) ſuggeſteth theſe cavils to the minde and the dazelling eye, is
<pb facs="tcp:847:7"/>ready to fixe it ſelfe upon them, as if they were mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſome weight and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or anſwers of good force. Be warned to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare thus to abuſe your wits to your owne hurt. Study to be able to defend your ſelves, and to learne how to doe it. What mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it, to lay ones naked brest open to his enemies weapon? Reject not the conſolations of God, neither let them ſeeme ſmall unto you. Know your ſelves tyed in conſcience, as to humble, and to purge, ſo likewiſe to comfort your ſelves, without which the former is done in
<pb facs="tcp:847:7"/>vaine, and the latter cannot be done at all. Be willing therefore to receive Gods goodneſſe, when it is made evident that you have inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thereunto. This is all I have to ſay in this Epiſtle. Now I leave you to the booke it ſelfe, beſeeching God to make you reade joy and gladneſſe, that your broken bones may rejoyce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>April</hi> 20. 1637.</note> and ſo wilreſt a well-wiſher to you all</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM WHATELY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:847:8"/>
            <p>Perlegi hunc tractatum in quo nihilreperio quò minùs cum utilitate imprimatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THO: WEEKES. R. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Epiſc. Lond. Cap. Domest.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:847:8"/>
            <head>THE OYLE OF GLADNESSE: <hi>OR</hi> Comfort for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected Sinners.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 SAM 12 24, 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And David</hi> comforter <hi>Bathſheba</hi> his wife and went in unto her and lay with bar, and ſhe hare a onne, and called his name <hi>Salomon</hi> and the Lord loved him.</p>
                  <p>And he ent by the band of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, and be called his name <hi>Iedidiah</hi> becauſe of the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen agood chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered ſore:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:847:9"/>Firſt, hee applyeth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſives and cleanſing things, to cate out the dead and proud fleſh, and to draw away the filth and putrifaction. This done, he layes healing playſters to perfect the cure. So did the Lord proceed with <hi>David,</hi> his wounds did ſtink and were putrified, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeakes in the Pſalme. The Lord had uſed reproofe by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> mouth, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by his own hand. Theſe ſharper medicines had wrought excellent well upon him, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:847:9"/>brought him to a ſerious confeſſion, and a ſolemne faſt of ſeven daies conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, (as in likely.) Now it was time to give him ſome comfort, and make him to heare joy and gladneſſe, that the broken bones might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. This is done in the verſes which I have read. And here he hath, firſt comfort in his owne minde, by which he was able to comfort <hi>Bathſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba.</hi> For he ſhould have beene a poore comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of her, unleſſe he had firſt comforted himſelfe: ſecondly outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:847:10"/>in giving him a ſon by her, and giving that ſonne two names, and that by the meſſage of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, one <hi>Shelomo,</hi> that is, peaceable or his peace, or the peace of the Lord, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Iedidiah,</hi> the Lord will love him, becauſe both God did love him, and he was to bee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of abundance of proſperity and peace to Iſrael; yea becauſe God would love him with a conſtant love; for <hi>Iedidiah</hi> ſignifies the Lord will make to love. And now the breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:847:10"/>God and <hi>David</hi> is fully made up. For in calling <hi>Salomon</hi> by that name, he would ſignifie that he was now at peace with <hi>David.</hi> And by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him <hi>Iedidiah,</hi> hee would ſignifie that the Lord did love him alſo. The words are plaine enough, and the matter will bee fuller under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, if you reade in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.9. where <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> tells <hi>Salomon,</hi> that God tels him that a ſon ſhould bee borne unto him, whoſe name ſhould be <hi>Salomon,</hi> and that hee would give him reſt and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:847:11"/>peace; whence it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant, that even before the childe was borne, GOD ſent to him to give him this name, and to let him underſtand, that this ſonne was hee that was meant in the former propheſie of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> who muſt raigne after him, and build the houſe of the Lord. Now this could not but exceedingly rejoyce <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to make him aſſured that God was reconciled to him, becauſe he would chooſe a ſonne of his, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the ſame wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, after the ſin, to be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:847:11"/>King after him, to build him a houſe.</p>
               <p>Now let us ſee what inſtructions we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of theſe words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§. I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAavid</hi> becomes a comforter of <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> by which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he was in good meaſure comforted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>We heard him confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſin, we ſaw him lying in the duſt, clothed with ſackcloth, tumbling in aſhes: Now you ſee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:847:12"/>him cheerefull againe ſpeaking cheerefully to <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and ſtriving to revive his drooping ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, for doubtleſſe ſhee was in fault as well as <hi>David,</hi> and when ſhee heard of <hi>Nathans</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, and ſaw her childes ſickeneſſe and death, ſhe cryed <hi>peccavi,</hi> and ſhe caſt downe her ſelfe as well as he.</p>
                  <p>Hence learne this leſſon</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§. 2.</head>
                  <p>That the people of God, having humbled themſelves after their ſins, muſt then labour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:847:12"/>alſo to take comfort.</p>
                  <p>When wee have caſt downe our ſelves before the Lord, and confeſſed and bewailed our offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, be they what they will, then muſt we raiſe vp our ſelves, and ſtrive to ſettle peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and gladneſſe in our hearts againe.</p>
                  <p>Conſolation ſhould follow mourning, and gladneſſe ſhould come after ſadneſſe.</p>
                  <p>If any Saint have fallen into ſome great ſinne, yet when he hath renewed his repentance for the ſinne, hee ſhould
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:847:13"/>againe take comfort in God, notwithſtanding that ſinne.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the inceſtuous <hi>Cortuths</hi> great griefe, writes to them <hi>to comfort him,</hi> and <hi>confirme their love to him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.8, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>that he might not be ſwallowed up of too much ſorrow.</hi> Loe there is a time when a man muſt wade out of his griefes, for feare of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drowned in them. Therefore you know our Saviour promiſeth to <hi>comfort them that mourne,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5.4.</note> and to give them the oyle of gladneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead<note place="margin">Iſa. 61.3.</note>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:847:13"/>of the garments of ſadneſſe: It is not Gods purpoſe to make his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple goe alwaies in black, hee would have them weare lightſomer co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours after a time.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee had ſeene the Lord in the way,<note place="margin">Acts 9.19</note> was in very great heavineſſe, for three daies and nights, but after, he was baptized, and took com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and began to preach Chriſt. The people <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 46. were pricked in heart, but we read af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that they did eate their meate with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:847:14"/>The <hi>Iayler</hi> parted cheerefully with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> though he had a lamentable meeting with them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>Now there is great reaſon that the Saints ſhould take comfort af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have taken griefe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon.</note> becauſe they have as good and ſure grounds and cauſes of comfort as of ſorrow. Secondly, becauſe they ſhall glorifie God as much. Thirdly, becauſe they ſhall profit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:847:14"/>as much by taking comfort as by their mourning.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, I ſay a good man that hath mourned, hath as great cauſe to take comfort as ever he had to mourne; for he hath the promiſes of God to the penitent, as well as his threats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſinner. He hath his mercy to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as well as his juſtice againſt the tranſgreſſor. He hath Chriſts prayers, merits, interceſſion to ſtand for him, as well as the cry and clamour of his ſinnes to ſtand againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:847:15"/>him. God hath as plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and as ſtrongly tyed himſelfe, to accept the repenting ſinner, as to puniſh the unrepenting: and hath as carneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired us to believe his promiſes as his threats, and is altogether as true in his promiſes, and as carefull to performe them, as to performe his threats. And it is the office and worke of the Spirit to be a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to convince of righteouſneſſe, as well as of ſinne. The Lord hath as plainely ſaid,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.21, 24.</note> 
                     <hi>If the wicked man neturne from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:847:15"/>his wicked waies he ſhall live; as if the righteous returne from his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he ſhall die.</hi> Hee hath promiſed refreſhing to all heavic laden, as well as threatned deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all wilfull and wicked tranſgreſſors, and <hi>to wound the hairy ſcalpe of ſuch an one as goeth on in his treſpaſſes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.21.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing the Lord offers himſelfe gratiouſly to them, therefore have they cauſe to enjoy theſe conſolations of his Word.</p>
                  <p>Yea the Apoſtle ſhewes that the Word
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:847:16"/>was written <hi>that through comfort of the Scriptures we might have hope.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> So that it may appeare that Gods chiefe end in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piling the Scripture, was to prepare comfort for the ſonnes of men, if they humble themſelves and become capable of it.</p>
                  <p>Yea the Spirit of God is called the <hi>Comforter,</hi> and God is called the <hi>God of all conſolation,</hi> and the God <hi>that comforteth the abject,</hi> all which grounds of conſolation being offered us, we are bound to receive them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:847:16"/>
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p>Againe, it is a worke as truly honourable to God, and maketh as much for his glory, that his people doe take the cup of conſolation at his hands, as that they drink the bitter cup of worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, yea and more too. For to grieve even for ſinne, further then it tends to comfort, and ends in it, is nothing at all to the glory of God of it ſelfe: for in hell they grieve enough, but that griefe is not in them a worke tending to Gods
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:847:17"/>glory, becauſe it aimes not at comfort, but is a deſperate forlorne and uncomfortable griefe. For in grieving for our ſinnes, we give God the glory of his juſtice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging them to be vile and loathſome and grievous. But in comforting our ſelves we give him the glory of his mercy, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him to be more full of goodneſſe, then our ſelves bee of bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which is to doe him the higheſt honour. For the Lord delighteth in ſhewing mercy, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:847:17"/>therefore cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light that men ſhould eſteeme and account him ſo ready to ſhew mercy. For whoſoever loveth to doe any good and commendable thing, loves to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ready and able to do that thing.</p>
                  <p>And indeed God is not well pleaſed nor honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as I ſaid before, with his Saints teares further then thoſe teares bee meanes of fitting them for, and making them capeable of comfort: As the Chyrurgion deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not in the ſmart of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:847:18"/>his patient further then it is a meanes of healing the ſore: nor the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian in the bitter potions of his patient, or his ſickneſſe, further then it procureth health. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (if we conſider) in the old Law,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.14.</note> he calleth vpon them to bee ſure that they doe rejoyce in their feaſts. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he appointed one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſolemne faſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the yeare,<note place="margin">Levit. 26.19.</note> and that but one daies continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance alone, he appointed three ſeverall moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne feaſts in every yeare; and thoſe alſo of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:847:18"/>ſeaven daies continuance each of them.<note place="margin">Exod. 23 14.</note> Whereby it is manifeſt that hee takes farre more content in their gladneſſe and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, then in their ruth and lamentation. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed hee liketh their griefes alone, as I ſaid before, as a preparative to their Joy.</p>
                  <p>Now ſeeing our care muſt be to doe that that may glorifie and pleaſe God, and our joyes will glorifie and pleaſe him, after wee have beene humbled, as well as our humiliation before: it is needfull for us to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:847:19"/>cheare up our hearts, as well as to depreſſe them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§ 5.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, this comfort is a thing altogether as profitable to our ſelves, and as much availeable to our ſanctification and good living, as griefe: nay griefe will doe at all no good to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of holineſſe and beating downe of ſinne, further then it is ſo orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and moderated, that it may conclude in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. As a man is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to doe any naturall work, when he hath his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:847:19"/>limmes all at eaſe and reſt: ſo to do any ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good thing, when he hath his minde at eaſe and reſt.<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.10.</note> 
                     <hi>The joy of the Lord is your ſtrength,</hi> ſaith that holy man to the people in <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> which is the cauſe that God hath confirmed his promiſe by oath, that as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.</note> 
                     <hi>wee might have ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The herbs and graſſe and corne doe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen beſt in warme and fun-ſhine weather: ſo the ſun-ſhine of conſolation, doth bring up the herbe of vertues in our hearts.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:847:20"/>Carnall and earthly joyes doe nothing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the growth of piety, but ſpirituall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, ſuch as this we intreate of doe make it proſper and flouriſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly. Never is a Chriſtian man in better caſe to doe any good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to beare any miſery for Gods ſake, to love God, to pray, to heare the Word, to doe works of mercy to the afflicted, or to performe any other ſervices, then when he can comfort himſelfe in God. Then the heart hath more full commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:847:20"/>with God, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is in beſt plight to doe any thing well. I confeſſe ſorrow hath its uſe, it is as plowing, and as breaking of the clods, that make the ground ready for the ſeed: It is as it were the ſweeping and cleanſing of the houſe, that maketh it fit for the Holy Ghoſt as for agueſt to inhabit and to dwell in. But the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proper confirmer and ſtrengthener of the ſoule is comfort: that doth miniſter to it ability to worke Gods works. As God loves, in matter of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:847:21"/>bounty, a cheerefull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: ſo in all ſervices a cheerefull ſervant. And doubtleſſe the ſervice will not be cheerefull if the heart be not comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: therefore in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where God hath the beſt ſervices, men have the moſt comfort. And in Paradice, where God had the beſt ſervice next to heaven, man had the moſt comfort. And in the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1 3, 6.</note> in whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did commend, the labour of love, the worke of faith, the patience of hope, and whom he praiſeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:847:21"/>their love and their faith did grow excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, hee ſhewes the foundation of this growth to have beene, becauſe they received the Word with joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>Seeing well-grounded comfort is the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable thing that can be for our ſoules, we muſt ſtrive for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>§ 6.</head>
                  <p>Onely brethren you muſt remember how we limited the point, <hi>viz.</hi> that after we have hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled our ſelves we muſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:847:22"/>then take comfort, and not before.</p>
                  <p>There is a time ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> to mourne and a time to laugh, we muſt take time to rend our hearts and to turne to the Lord with mourning and contrition; and then we muſt take time alſo to ſtirre up, and to revive our hearts, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Lords mercies with all joyfullneſſe: we muſt beware of making too much haſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelves, as alſo of being too ſlow to the worke. If the ſore bee not throughly drawne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:847:22"/>before it be healed, then the feſtered matter will breake out againe, and the cure will not be well effected, and if it be not healed after drawing, no ſoundneſſe will come to the member affected. As the body, ſo the ſoule muſt be healed ſoundly, and to the bottome, and not skinned over with untimely and prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ungrounded conſoations.</p>
                  <p>I pray you to obſerve this caution and this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, that none of you may abuſe, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply the point to your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:847:23"/>owne hurt, for nothing is more dangerous then falſe comfort. Of the twaine, it is much more ſafe, though it ſeeme far more troubleſome, to be too much and too long in mourning, then to fetch in comfort before we have at all mourned, or before we have mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in due meaſure: for to comfort ones ſelfe untimely, is to truſt in a lie, and is the ſureſt way to cut off all ſound and good comfort, and to keepe a mans ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of true comfort. Thus daubing with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:847:23"/>morter will never make any good worke, downe will that daubing come, in the day when the ſtorme and winde ſhall blow upon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§ 7.</head>
                  <p>If any man aske how he ſhall be ſure not to take comfort too ſoone, I anſwer him:</p>
                  <p>That he muſt not bee bold to take any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, till he have gotten ſuch a meaſure of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and let ſorrow con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſo long in his heart, that it hath wrought him
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:847:24"/>to a plaine, and free, and full confeſſion of his ſins to God, and to a firme and ſtedfaſt purpoſe and determination of will, to leave, forſake and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them. And when he hath brought himſelfe to this, then muſt hee mixe his ſorrow with ſome comfort, and after a while he muſt bid his griefes adew, and feed conſtantly and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally upon comforts, renewing his griefes at fit times and ſeaſons (as it were dipping in ſome ſharpe ſauce to keepe him from ſurfeting) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:847:24"/>retaining an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled heart in the ſight of ſinne, but not alwaies a ſad heart; for as the heart may be ſad, and not humbled: ſo it may bee humbled and not ſad.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> BVt now for Vſe of the point.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§ 1.</head>
                  <p>Firſt, it gives cauſe of a gentle reprehenſion to many of Gods ſervants, that keepe on their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſorrow too long, and ſtill feed on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:847:25"/>wormewood and gall, almoſt refuſing to bee comforted, then, when comfort is due to them. Though they have ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched their hearts and confeſſed their ſinnes, and brought their hearts to a full purpoſe of amendment; yet they faile in that they doe not take ſome meaſure of comfort to themſelves, and doe not partake of the conſolations of God which he offers to them in his holy Word.</p>
                  <p>There are ſome that make too much haſte to comfort themſelves, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:847:25"/>ſome that doe not make haſt enough. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, and the greater fault, is, to put away ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes too ſoone: yet that of putting away comfort too farre and too long from the ſoule is a fault alſo, and muſt not be denied where it is. Many of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple I ſay are exceſſive in their mourning, even for their ſinnes, in that when they have true right to comfort, and God doth ſpeake peace unto them, yet they doe not give reſt and peace unto their owne ſoules,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:847:26"/>but ſurfit upon worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood and bitterneſſe, and thruſt comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from themſelves through unbeliefe. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times men mourne too much and too long for croſſes (that point doth not now come to bee handled) and ſometimes they mourne as thoſe that have no hope, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſinnes, and that is the fault we have now to declare and to reproove.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§ 2.</head>
                  <p>Know then O yee ſervants of God, that when you doe even tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:847:26"/>your ſelves, and keepe your hearts ſtill upon the racke as it were, you doe greatly diſhonour God, in this unmeaſurable mourning, and greatly hurt your ſelves too. For what? is there not goodneſſe in God as well as Iuſtice? Is he made all of anger? <hi>Are his mercies cleane gone for ever? Hath he ſhut up his tender compaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in diſpleaſure?</hi> It is a diſcredit to the maſter of the family if his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be alwaies ſad and whining: For if they had a good and mercifull
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:847:27"/>Maſter, why ſhould they be ſtill languiſhing and complaining? See then, that ye doe offend in this caſe, by not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the infinite mercies and tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions of your God. For in not comforting your ſelves, you doe actually deny him to bee mercifull. For if he be mercifull, why doe wee not taſte and feele how good he is?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>And take notice that in not comforting your ſelves you be alſo injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to your own ſoules:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:847:27"/>You make your ſelves unfit to ſerve God, in any good duty, unfit to pray, unfit to heare, unfit to live, unfit to die, by being ſtill heavie and diſcouraged. When the ſoule goes mourning and bowed downe to the ground, ſtill in feare that God will not accept, and will not pardon, it lies open to manifold temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to murmuring, to wearineſſe of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to impatiency, to frowardneſſe, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſet it ſelfe reſolutely, to doe the worke of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:847:28"/>Thou hindreſt the growth of grace in thy ſelfe, for want of faire weather as it were. Thou makeſt the fruits of the Spirit to be farre leſſe and fewer then they would be, becauſe they have not warmth enough to bring them up. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art to reprehend thy ſelf and to ſay, <hi>This is my weakeneſſe and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> this is my fault verily, which I muſt not excuſe but acknowledge and blame in my ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> If any ſay alaſſe I would comfort my ſelfe if I
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:847:28"/>could, I doe not deſire to go languiſhing, but oh I cannot chooſe, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of ſin is ſo preſſing, &amp; lies ſo hard upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> I anſwer, the thing that thou muſt bee bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for, is not becauſe thou art not actually comforted, for therein thou muſt be a patient and take it when it comes, even when God will give it, but becauſe thou doſt not ſet thy ſelfe to enjoy comfort, that thou doſt not offer to thy minde the conſolations of God, and doſt not take paines to binde up
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:847:29"/>thy broken and rent heart. I ſay thou doſt not take paines to get comfort, but yeeldeſt unto ſorrow, and hangeſt downe thine hands, and ſuffereſt thy knees to be feeble. Thou doſt not call to mind the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God. Thou doſt not ponder upon the death of Chriſt. Thou doſt not entertaine ſuch thoughts as are fit to bring comfort to thy ſoule, but ſelleſt over thy ſelfe to ſadd and fearefull &amp; diſcouraging thoughts; ſtill ſtill looking to the greatneſſe and multitude
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:847:29"/>of thy ſinnes, and not rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thine eyes to, and fixing thy thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mercies and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſes of God, not earneſtly imploring and begging the helpe of his Spirit to comfort thee, and this is thy fault, (ariſing from hence, that thou art too ready to hearken to Satan, who doth lye unto thee, and denies thine intereſt unto comfort.) Now ſuffer a gentle and mild reproofe for it, and know it to bee a fault; for why ſhouldſt thou not enjoy thine own portion and take that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:847:30"/>that God giveth thee. If thou anſwereſt ſtill, I cannot, I cannot. I anſwer ſtill thou canſt labour, ſtrive, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and thy not labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and endeavouring is that that is blamed in thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§ 5.</head>
                  <p>As in outward croſſes wee are often too pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory mourners (and with <hi>Iacob</hi> will not bee comforted) and reſolve, we will goe mourning to the grave. So ſometimes in regard of ſinnes, wee will not be comforted.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:847:30"/>Sometimes this ariſeth from an error in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe we thinke not our ſelves to have any intereſt unto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, when we have, and are afraid to take it, leaſt it ſhould not belong to us. Many times Gods people thinke they have not cauſe to take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, when they have, and therefore put com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from themſelves, becauſe they miſtake their owne eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>§ 6.</head>
                  <p>But tell me haſt thou not afflicted thy ſelfe?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:847:31"/>haſt thou not wept and mourned? haſt thou not turned thy laughter into ſorrow, and thy Joy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heavineſſe? haſt thou not caſt downe thy ſelfe before the Lord? and found out and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged all thy faults againſt thy ſelfe, (ſo farre as by ſearching thou waſt able to find them.)</p>
                  <p>If thy ſoule can ſay I have laboured to ſee all my ſinnes; and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to confeſſe and weepe for them, and complained of them, and ſhamed my ſelfe and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:847:31"/>judged my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> Then I aske againe haſt thou not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced thy ſelfe, and all thine owne merits?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes htat I have too.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> Haſt thou not reſolved to take Chriſt youake? haſt thou not made a Covenant with God, to fight againſt thy ſinnes, and to reforme and amend thy life, and make they heart and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit new?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes that I have too, I have reſolved, but alaſſe I find little power.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, upon thy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:847:32"/>reſolution to obey after mourning and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, thou haſt intereſt to comfort, and it muſt bee comfort that muſt ſtrengthen thy reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and confirme thee in obedience.</p>
                  <p>Now then ſee thy miſtaking, and know thou art one to whom comfort is due, and let not error over-ſhadow the ſunne of comfort from ſhining upon thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§ 7.</head>
                  <p>Another cauſe of not being comforted is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, the moourners can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:847:32"/>believe that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts appertaine to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: but this is a fault too. For why? doth not God call to him, all that be heavie laden with ſin; and in calling them to him, even bind them to take comfort?</p>
                  <p>Indeed the divell en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies the comfort of the Saints, and ſeeketh to hinder it with multitude of objections. And ſome of Gods people bee ſo weake, that they ſuffer the divell to have his will on them this way, and hearken too much to his leaſenings. But
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:847:33"/>now, ſee that this is a fault, that doth even diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace piety to many, and make them thinke that godlineſſe, and joy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dwell in one heart, ſo that they refuſe piety for feare of wanting joy, whereas no companions will better agree then theſe two.</p>
                  <p>I have beene long in this reproofe, and yet as you ſee, milde and gentle enough. It is a weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it is a frailty. It is a thing hurtfull and offenſive, take notice of it, and reprehend thy ſelfe for it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:847:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§ 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> ANd ſecondly, let me nowpreſſe the Saints of God to follow <hi>David</hi> in the paths of conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You heard him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, you ſaw him in aſhes, now you ſee him chearefull againe.</p>
                  <p>Haſt thou followed him in that heavie path? follow him in this glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Now that the Lord pipeth to thee, ſee that thou dance. Now that God biddeth thee take comfort, ſee that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:847:34"/>thou take it. Coe hither all yee Saints, that have long beene clad in black, and have rolled your ſelves in aſhes, and have mingled your drinke with teares: Come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and learne of <hi>David</hi> to comfort your ſelves: O heare joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and let your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken bones rejoyce. You I ſay that have ſate in darkeneſſe, that have wept and wailed, that with bitter ſighs and ſalt teares have blamed and ſhamed your ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, come hither now, and behold <hi>David,</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:847:34"/>and follow him, put on thegarments of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and comfort your ſelves in Gods mercy. It is as needfull and as plaine a duty to believe Gods promiſes as his threats, to acknowledge his goodneſſe as your owne badneſſe. You have done the one, now doe the other alſo, and let everlaſting joy be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your heads. Doth not Chriſt tell thee, that hee came to comfort the mourners? hee is here now in his Ordinances to comfort thee: ô let him not comfort thee in vaine.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:847:35"/>
                  <p>Sitrre up thy ſelfe, and ſay, Iought to take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and Lord through thine helpe, I will take comfort to my ſelfe, and give thee the glory of the riches of thy grace in Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§ 2.</head>
                  <p>If any ſay, but I can feele no comfort. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Thou muſt believe it firſt, and then thou muſt feele it after. Firſt, thou muſt draw out of Gods booke happie condluſions of comfort. That thy ſinnes are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, that God is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:847:35"/>reconciled, that thy ſoule ſhall bee ſaved, and then muſt ſo preſſe and urge theſe concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon thy ſoule, and binde thy ſelfe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them, that in time ſence of comfort may follow after.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>Now that you may be able to comfort your ſelves againſt ſinnes, and the feare of Gods wrath and damnation for them, (for you ſee that the Text calleth us to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that comfort, you
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:847:36"/>muſt take notice of foure things needfull to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men in comforting themſelves when they be made fit for comfort. Firſt, one notable impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to comfort whereof you muſt take heede. Secondly, the true ground of comfort. Thirdly, the degrees by which comfort groweth. Laſtly, the meanes of comforting your ſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. For the firſt, if you will take comfort in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, you muſt reſolve to beleeve neither the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:847:36"/>divell, not the fleſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to credit Satan nor your owne hearts, but onely God, ſpeaking in his holy Word.</p>
                  <p>The divell is a knowne, and wilfull, and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed lyar, and alwaies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt frameth his tale againſt turth.</p>
                  <p>If he meete with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that feeleth not ſinne at all; hee will flatter him with falſe hopes, and make him (if he can) to beleeve that all is well, and that God will ſhew mercy to him, though he have no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of right unto it. And
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:847:37"/>by his good will hee would have men lulled a ſleepe, with theſe falſe and vaine and worthleſſe comforts, even till their dying day. But when he cannot hold them any longer in this ſweete dreame, but that they begin to ſee and to feele ſinne, and to feare Gods judgements; then hee will tell them a quite contrary tale. That there is no hope, that the time is paſt, that God will not receive them, taht their offences afe unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that it is in vaine to ſeeke mercy, that the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:847:37"/>date of grace is gone and paſt, that ſo if it were poſſible they might bee drowned in deſpaite, Wherefore whoſoever would finde comfort muſt ſtop his eares againſt Satan, and reſolve to beleeve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he ſayes.</p>
                  <p>Thou foundeſt him a lyer in his comforts, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, now know him a lyer too in his preſent terrors. Hee is equally falſe when hee roares as when he ſings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:847:38"/>
                  <head>§ 5.</head>
                  <p>Againe, beleeve not thy ſelfe, (thine owne heart) for that is falſe and deceitfull and full of error. Thou muſt not conclude I have no inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt unto comfort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I thinke I have none. Gods waies are not our waies, nor his thoughts our thoughts: What we thinke, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters nor, but what hee ſaith in his Word. Thou mayeſt ſee the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of thine owne heart alſo by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, doſt thou not know
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:847:38"/>well, that thy heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived thee heretofore, in telling thee, that all was well with thee, when thy caſe was very miſerable? Did it lie then, in miniſtring to thee ungrounded and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſolations? then know, that it is as likely to lie at this time, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying comfort to thee. So farre as we ſuffer our eares to be open to the ſuggeſtions of Satan, and to the conceits of our owne hearts, ſo farre we hinder our ſelves of comfort. But we muſt ſay, <hi>I will heare what God
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:847:39"/>ſaith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.8.</note> 
                     <hi>he will ſpeake peace.</hi> I will believe him and not the divell, not my ſelfe. Well now thus the heart is ſet in way of taking ocmfort.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>§ 6.</head>
                  <p>Now in the ſecond place, I will ſhew you the ground and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſpirituall comfort, whereof we are now ſpeaking. There is indeed, a comfort againſt outward evills, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt other ſorrowes then thoſe for ſinne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, many things might well bee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:847:39"/>ſpoken, but I have not to doe with them at this time. Alone I am to ſhew the ſole baſe and ground-worke of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort, which is the ſtedfaſt and aſſured apprehenſion or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the remiſſion of our ſinnes, and the love and favour of God in Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal</hi> 30.1</note> This <hi>David</hi> proveth, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſinnes are covered, whoſe iniquity is pardoned, and to whom the Lord imputeth no ſinne,</hi> And againe, having ſaid <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. <hi>Make mee to heare joy and gladneſſe that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:847:40"/>the bones which thou haſt broken may rejoyce,</hi> hee adds immediately, <hi>Hide thy face from my ſinnes,</hi> ver. 9. The ſame our Saviour declareth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaying to the poore Palſy-man, <hi>Sonne bee of good comfort thy ſinnes be forgiven thee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 9.2.</note> and to that ſorrowfull weeping wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Goſpell (who made her eyes as it were a yewre to waſh his feet) <hi>Daughter thy ſinnes are forgiven.</hi> There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſuffcient to beare up true comfort, but a true and well grounded aſſurance, of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:847:40"/>goodneſſe of God, which is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits. And as any mans ſoule hath a more ſolid and ſtedfaſt and well built perſwaſion of this mercy: ſo is he the more comfortable, at leaſt more capeable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: as hee hath leſſe firme or leſſe true know-ledge of this, ſo is hee leſſe fit and able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive conſolation. So then this concluſion muſt be written in the heart, <hi>God hath pardoned my ſinnes, and received me gratiouſly in Chriſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:847:41"/>afore it can bee duely comforted, and ſo you ſee the ground of the comfort we ſeeke for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§ 7.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, I will ſhew you by what degrees this comfort groweth in the heart uſually. When a mans ſinnes lie moſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie upon his ſoule, and that the law like a ſword hath ripped up and laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his very heart that it runs and bleeds againe; then he heareth the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpell, teaching remiſſion of ſins by Ieſus Chriſt, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:847:41"/>doth aſſent to the truth of it, as that it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted verity, and then ſtrives to apply it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and hath a ſecret perſwaſion that it ſhall be performed even to himſelfe, now this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion groweth up in three degrees.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the promiſe makes him thinke with himſelfe, Aſſuredly my ſinnes may be pardoned: The righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is ſufficient to juſtifie me, and God can accept and forgive me. This makes him runne crying and praying to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:847:42"/>God for pardon, and affoords a little glimme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of comfort, as when a ſick man knowes his diſeaſe to be curable, and that the Phyſitian can cure him, this is one graine of faith.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to pray to God for aſpace, he then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth a little ſtronger hope, and ſaith in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>I hope God will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me,</hi> which makes him yet more warme in in his ſuit, and bringeth a little more conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this is an other graine of faith.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:847:42"/>
                  <p>Laſtly, he begins to conclude, <hi>God hath pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me;</hi> at firſt, making this concluſion feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (not without admix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of many doubts, which he reſiſteth, and laboureth to reject) and at length with more ſtrength and leſſe doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till he attaine a very full aſſurance, that ſcarce findeth any wavering, and then hath his ſoule a ſtrong conſolation, even a full weight of comfort.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have ſhewed you the third thing I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that no man
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:847:43"/>may bee diſcomforted utterly, becauſe he is not at firſt able perfectly to comfort himſelfe, as ſometimes good people are, thinking that they have no faith becauſe they have not the higheſt degree thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§ 1.</head>
                  <p>NOw in the fourth place, I will tell you by what meanes you muſt ſtrengthen your
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:847:43"/>faith, that it may affoord you large and ſtrong conſolation: for though no labour of man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power of Gods Spirit can worke this comfort, yet doth the Spirit of God beget it, by meanes of ſuch holy labours and endeavours as himſelfe incites us to. Theſe meanes are chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly foure: Meditation, Prayer, Conference, and a due information of judgement concerning this matter of remiſſion of ſins.</p>
                  <p>The firſt then is Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, and that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:847:44"/>of foure things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of the perfect me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Ieſus Chriſt. 2. Of the infinite mercies of God. 3. Of the large and unlimited promiſes of the Word. 4. Of Gods gratiouſneſſe to other ſinners, out of all which ſound conſolation may be taken, by the moſt broken heart that is or can be.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§ 2.</head>
                  <p>The firſt thing then to be ſeriouſly pondered upon is, the perfection of Chriſts merits, for upon this foundation
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:847:44"/>doth comfort moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. For our ſelves it matters not what we have deſerved, or can deſerve, for it muſt be confeſſed that our deſerts extend to nothing but ruine and deſtruction. But our Lord and ſurety Ieſus Chriſt hath made a full and perfect ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God, and deſerved full and perfect remiſſion of ſinnes for all that ſeeke unto him. For of him the Scripture beareth witneſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 3. ult.</note> 
                     <hi>That in him God is well pleaſed, and that by him all that beleeve,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 13.38, 39.</note> 
                     <hi>are juſtified from
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:847:45"/>all things, from which they could not bee juſtified by the law of</hi> Moſes. <hi>And him hath God ſet forth to be a propitiation through faith in his bloud.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee hath redeemed us from the curſe of the law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 3 1</note> 
                     <hi>being made a curſe for us.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30.</note> 
                     <hi>Alſo He is our Wiſedome, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Sanctification and Redemption. And in Him wee have redemption through his bloud,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ 1.7</note> 
                     <hi>the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes. And He hath taken away the ſinnes of the world.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 1.29</note> 
                     <hi>And His bloud cleanſeth us from all ſinne.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh 1 7</note> 
                     <hi>And He is able to the uttermoſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> 
                     <hi>to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:847:45"/>ſave thoſe that come unto God by him.</hi> All theſe places doe teſtifie the fullneſſe and abſolute perfection of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>that as by the ſinne of one man, the firſt</hi> Adam, <hi>many have beene made ſinners, ſo by the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of one man the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> Adam,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.9.</note> 
                     <hi>many be made righteous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now as it is in the caſe of a debtor and of his ſurety, ſo it is betwixt God and us in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Though the debtor being a meere banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, cannot poſſibly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:847:46"/>diſcharge his owne debt, yet if his ſurety have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made payment of all his debts, or fully diſcharged them, he is ſafe enough from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: So, though we be utterly deſtitute of all ability to ſatisfie for our ſinnes, and to deſerve pardon of them; yet if our ſurety Ieſus Chriſt have fully ſatisfied for them, as he hath, there is hope enough of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pardoned. For our Lord Ieſus Chriſt was both God and man, a perſon infinitely more excellent then all men,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:847:46"/>and therefore his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and obedience are of ſuch infinite worth and valew, that by him the wrath of God is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeaſed towards us. For it was a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of Gods juſtice to puniſh him his onely begotten Sonne for our ſinnes in ſuch ſort as he did, as if he had puniſhed us to all eternity. Suppoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers debtors, one owing 10000 lb. another 5000 another 1000 another 100 lb. ſome more, ſome leſſe, but each one more then his ſubſtance could
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:847:47"/>poſſibly ſatisfie: yet if ſome able perſon had laid downe divers Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of farre greater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew then all their debts did amount unto, then were their debts ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwered for, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther need they be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged at the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them. Even ſo, when we have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted innumerable ſinnes, deſerving eternall death, and can no way ſatisfie for our ſelves, yet ſo long as he hath perfectly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the law for us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made under the law in our ſteed, and hath
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:847:47"/>perfectly ſatisfied the juſtice of God by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the curſe for us; our eſtate is good enough in him, though never ſo irrecoverable in our ſelves. Wherefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſins to Chriſts merits, and thinke, is not he my Saviour? hath not he diſcharged my debt? hath not he anſwered for mine offences? are not his death, ſufferings, and obedience, much more able to pacifie Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to provoke it? Doubtleſſe it is ſo: no man that profeſſeth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:847:48"/>Chriſtian Religion will deny it, and therefore by his bloud peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may come unto the greateſt ſinner.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>If it be objected, Ah, J know his redemption is perfect and all-ſurficient, but how can I tell that it ſhall be granted unto me? I anſwer, put off that queſtion a little, till thou have firſt anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome few queſtions which I ſhall propound unto thee. Doſt not thou thinke that the bloud of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:847:48"/>Chriſt is ſufficient to waſh away all thy ſins? is not his ſatisfaction full, compleate and of worth enough to anſwer for all thy tranſgreſſions, even though they were more then they bee? If thou ſayeſt no, thou denyeſt the truth of the fore-alledged Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and diſparageſt the merits of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, which I hope thou wilt not dare to doe: but if yea, as needs thou muſt ſay yea, then hearken yet further a little, and for thine owne intereſt into this ſatisfaction, receive
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:847:49"/>ſatisfaction by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Our Saviour Chriſt calleth unto him, all that travell and are heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with ſin, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth refreſhing &amp; reſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſoules. Tell me, art not thou laden? art not thou cruſhed? Doſt not thou confeſſe thy ſins to be a moſt inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burden, and ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie a loade that they will ſurely preſſe thee downe to hell, if he doe not eaſe thee? if thou doſt not or doſt not deſire ſo to doe thou art none of them whom I intend to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, if thou doſt, why
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:847:49"/>then in Gods name, let that loving invitation of our Lord ſatisfie thy forementioned doubt, and conclude thou thus for thy ſelfe. Every one that being heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den will come unto Chriſt, ſhall bee refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, ſhall have reſt to his ſoule, and therefore ſhall have his merits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there can bee no reſt to his ſoule. Now I am heavy laden, and I will runne to Chriſt (and ſo doe J pray thee, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting or feare any longer) and then
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:847:50"/>thou muſt conclude in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly, I ſhall be refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, I ſhall have the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt to be mine, according to the truth of his promiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p>And ſo you have the firſt meditation. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond muſt be of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercies of God in Chriſt, who is gratiouſly ready in him, the Sonne of his loves, to accept of every ſinner that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing himſelfe, and all his owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth flie wholy to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:847:50"/>him for refuge. For the Lord is a God,<note place="margin">Exod. 14 6.</note> 
                     <hi>gratious &amp; mercifull, ſlowe to anger, abundant in kindneſſe and truth, reſerving mercy for thouſands, forgiving ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, tranſgreſsion and ſinne.</hi> His mercy is as <hi>high above us as heaven is above the earth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal 103 11.</note> 
                     <hi>He will abundantly forgive,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.7, 2, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>and his waies are not as our waies, nor his thoughts as our thoughts, for as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are higher then the earth, ſo are his waies higher then our waies, and his thoughts above our thoughts.</hi> Yea hee hath multitude of tender
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:847:51"/>compaſſions, and is <hi>rich in mercy to all that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 10 12.</note> and his mercy endureth for ever. You ſee by theſe words of Scripture what ſtore of mercy there is in God, and what quantity of compaſſion poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that are humbled, muſt looke to finde with him. Now conſider further, what is this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compaſſion of God? Doubtleſſe it is a willingneſſe, prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, readineſſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, full reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to accept of miſerable ſinners that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:847:51"/>have made themſelves moſt wretched by their ſinnes, and to relieve their miſeries when they humbly ſtoope unto him. Mercy is not an ability to pardon and helpe if one will, but a willingneſſe to helpe and pardon when one is able. Wee doe not call him a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, that could help a poore diſtreſſed perſon if he would, but it is not his pleaſure ſo to doe, for ſo it may be with a moſt cruell and hard hearted fellow. The moſt rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and exating rich Uſurer, could forgive
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:847:52"/>his debtor (that is a banckerout and can pay him nothing) if hee would, but he will not though he can, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth not deſerve to be called mercifull. The moſt fierce and furious tyrant might forgive his ſubject, if he would, that hath offended, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not willing, therefore no man ſtyles him pitifull and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. So neither were the God of heaven full of grace, mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, if onely he were able to forgive humbled ſinners, and would not;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:847:52"/>that were not mercy I ſay, that were not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, but this is grace, this is compaſſion. He is willing to receive the humbled wretch, he is ready to forgive, and fully reſolved with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to blot out all his ſinnes from his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, bee they what they will for number or haighnouſnes, when once he converteth unto him. Now therefore that thou knoweſt the ſtore of mercy that is in God, and alſo what mercy is. Compare thy ſinnes alſo to Gods mercy, and ſee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:847:53"/>if they can be in any ſort equall thereunto. For are not his mercies in Chriſt infinite, endleſſe, boundleſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore farre ſurpaſſing all the ſinnes of all ſinners, which bee they, what they can be, for weight and number, yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe infinite they cannot bee.</p>
                  <p>Thou ſeeſt how great a thing this globe of earth and water ſeemeth to be to them that walke upon it, yet in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the heavenly ſpheare that doth incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe it, what is it elſe, but
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:847:53"/>a poynt, a prick, a center, a thing of nothing, that holdeth no proportion to thoſe higher regions, and know aſſuredly, that there is no more propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt all the ſins of all men, and Gods mercies, then betwixt the poynt of earth, and the circumference of the skies. He is willing to pardon more then all of them can commit, and therefore onely they bee not pardoned, becauſe they will not humble themſelves to ſeeke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Thus then muſt thou raiſe up thy falling
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:847:54"/>heart, I have to doe with a moſt infinitely mercifull and tender hearted Father, that doth not deſire the death of him that dieth, but is ten thouſand thouſand times more willing to give me pardon then I am to crave or accept it. It pleaſeth him more to beſtow forgiveneſſe, then me to receive it. O doe not ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to God, as to ſet any bounds and limits to his goodneſſe, to diminiſh or detract from the boundleſneſſe of his compaſſion, to thinke
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:847:54"/>that thou canſt poſſibly exceed his goodneſſe with thy badneſſe, but go unto him and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſaying, O Lord, the multitude of thy mercies doe farre ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the multitude of my rebellions, O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be gratious to mee according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy mercies, and ſo thou ſhalt bee ſafe.</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt ſay perhaps how can I tell that God will ſhew mercy to me? I anſwer, Art not thou one of thoſe to whom he hath ſealed up mercy
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:847:55"/>in baptiſme? yea but thou wilt ſay, many are baptized that never finde mercy. I anſwer, not one that in ſence of want of mercy, and in a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that God can bee mercifull to him, doth ſeeke to the throne of grace for it. And for a fuller anſwer to this doubt, now proceed to the third meditation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§ 5.</head>
                  <p>This is of the wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and largeneſſe of Gods promiſes to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which are of ſuch
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:847:55"/>an unlimited extent, that they exclude no ſinner for no ſinne, and in no time of comming to him. For in all theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, are his promiſes wondrous large and of great extent. J ſay firſt they ſhut not out any ſinner, but runne in this generality, Come unto me <hi>(All)</hi> that are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie laden, even all, all without any exception, ſo that whoſoever he be that is heavy laden, hee ſees the gate of Gods goodneſſe ſtanding open to him, and wide enough to receive even him alſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:847:56"/>among the reſt of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; next hee excepts not any ſinne, but telleth us thus, <hi>The bloud of Chriſt purgeth us from all ſinne.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7</note> And againe, <hi>if your ſinnes were as red as ſcarlet they ſhall bee as white as ſnow.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.18.</note> And againe,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.22.</note> 
                     <hi>I will blot all his iniquities out of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> and he bids them pray thus, <hi>Take away all iniquity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.2.</note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>David</hi> to cry and ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.9</note> 
                     <hi>Blot out all mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi> Doe you not heare how generall theſe promiſes bee, not nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed with any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:847:56"/>but alone to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood with this quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the perſons, if they be humbled for ſin. And in like manner for the time of comming lies not the promiſe, in the <hi>day that the ſinner turneth?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.12.</note> meaning when ſo ever, ſooner or later, firſt or laſt, ſo that hee turne in truth, you ſee no time excepted for the grant of pardon of ſinne. Indeed in regard of croſſes, it may fall out, that a man may ſeek to God for freedome of them and not find it, but for pardon of ſinnes, he
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:847:57"/>that comes in truth, comes never too late. And here now is the right uſe of thoſe univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall promiſes, which are ſet downe in Scripture. God would have no man periſh, <hi>but would have all men ſaved and come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4.</note> and <hi>He is a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſinnes of the whole world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.2.</note> and Hee gave <hi>himſelfe a ranſome for all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.6.</note> and He <hi>taſted death for every man.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 2.9.</note> Which the Lord hath of ſet purpoſe conceived in this ample forme of words, that there might
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:847:57"/>bee ſure and certaine ground and footing, for the faith of any man whatſoever, that being tyred with his ſinnes, doth runne unto this grace of God in Chriſt to finde helpe in time of need. Seeing God hath not excepted thy perſon, or thy faults, or thy time of comming, doe not thou except thy ſelfe, make not the gate of Gods promiſes ſcanter, or narrower then it is. He hath opened both the leaves of theſe dores as wide as may bee, and thinkes it not fit to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:847:58"/>cloze them up, againſt any humbled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing ſinner, at any time: O doe no thou put a diſtruſtfull hand upon them, to ſhut them againſt thy ſelfe, but let them ſtand wide open, and enter boldly, and aske mercy, and looke for mercy, and finde it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>§ 6.</head>
                  <p>Now followes the laſt meditation, which muſt be of the examples of Gods grace, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming theſe promiſes to other ſinners, as bad,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:847:58"/>if not worſe then any of us can be. For the Lord hath made good theſe words of his in his Son to as great, hainous, will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, preſumptuous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, as any have beene, are or can bee in the world, that will come unto him. No man can name, ſo great a ſinne or ſinnes, with ſo great ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, but that the Scriptures affoord us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of as grievous ſinnes pardoned, and as grievous ſinners ſaved, if they have framed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to humiliation and converſion. For what
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:847:59"/>may thy ſin bee or thine obſtinacy in ſin? Is it murder and adultery runne into with fore-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved deliberation? continued in with great hardneſſe and obdurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? behold theſe were <hi>Davids</hi> faults, and thou ſeeſt him pardoned and comforted, yea though he ran unto them in old age after many benefits received, and after a long time of forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſervice of God. Haſt thou beene an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later? a Buggerer? a Drunkard? a Rayler? an
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:847:59"/>Extortioner? why ſuch were ſome of the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers them) and yet they were waſhed, ſanctified, juſtified, as he alſo tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them. Haſt thou beſides Idolatry fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Sorcerers and Witches? and practiſed inchantments and ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? and that with ſo much and ſo long ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, as to kill thoſe that ſhould admoniſh thee of theſe faults? Why ſo did <hi>Manaſſes</hi> too, and yet he is pardoned. Haſt thou perſecuted Chriſt? blaſphemed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:847:60"/>him? made others to blaſpheme? and put them to death that would not? why ſo did <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, (and that after divers yeares ſpent in thoſe places, where many wonders and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles were wrought to confirme the Goſpell of Chriſt) and yet he is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. Haſt thou beene an harlot? ſo was <hi>Rahab,</hi> and the ſinnefull woman in the Goſpell. Haſt thou beene a theefe? ſo was hee that defended Chriſt on the Croſſe. Haſt thou denied and foreſworne Chriſt? ſo
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:847:60"/>did <hi>Peter</hi> alſo after hee had beene diverſe yeares his diſciple, and yet all theſe are pardoned. Yea verily brethren, the firſt ſinne that ever was committed, was in many reſpects the greateſt of all particular acts of ſin that ever were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſince. It was virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, radically, cauſally all ſinne, and yet loe <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Evah</hi> that did commit it, they are ſaved. The ſmalneſſe of the matter makes the fault farre greater, being a light and eaſie thing, propounded meerely for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:847:61"/>a triall, and as a ſigne and profeſſion of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as if a man ſhould forbid his childe a very ſlender thing, and that which hee might eaſily forbeare, to teſtifie his obedience unto him, he would be more offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt him in this caſe, by how much hee had made choyce of a more triviall matter to proove his obedience withall. Now for ſuch perſons at ſuch a time, in ſuch a place, in ſuch a ſtate, on ſuch motives to diſobey their maker in ſuch a thing, ſo eaſie to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:847:61"/>bee obſerved, and given to them onely to proove their obedience, ſurely a greater diſobedience (and therefore a greater ſinne) can hardly be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and yet as I ſaid before, this ſinne is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and thoſe ſinners ſaved. And who now can be hopeleſſe? who now can caſt off com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort? Now therfore ſtay and look upon thoſe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects &amp; proofes of Gods mercy and truth, and ſay unto thy ſelfe, is not God the ſame God that of old? was not his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and anger againſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:847:62"/>ſin, as great then as now? and is not his mercy and truth, as large and ſure now as then? and why then ſhould not J alſo take heart, to ſeeke unto the ſame God and reſt upon him. And theſe be the moſt comfortable meditations that I could propound, to the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and fearefull heart of the broken ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for the ſuppling of his wounds, and fitting his ſoule for conſolation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:847:62"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§ 1.</head>
                  <p>NOw theſe meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and intermixed, with confeſſions and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications. The poore ſinner muſt gather up his thoughts into petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and requeſts, and refuſing to be hindered by any feares, doubts, or objections, muſt take to himſelfe boldneſſe to fall downe before the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:847:63"/>throne of grace, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the counſell of the Holy Ghoſt, muſt take to himſelfe words, and ſay, receive me gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, and take away all iniquity. Addreſſe thy ſelfe unto the God of heaven in the name of Chriſt his Sonne, and ſay, Lord behold here the worſt of ſinners, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing before thee, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting himſelfe as low as hell, deſirons to bee as full of ſhame and ſorrow as is poſſible, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore troubled, becauſe he cannot be more grieved &amp; more abaſed. I am Lord
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:847:63"/>indeed a vile and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſinner, and theſe and theſe evills have I done, but ô for the merits ſake of Jeſus Chriſt alone, thy deere and onely begotten Sonne, accept me, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and according to the multitude of thy mercies, waſh mee throughly from all my ſinnes. Remember O Lord the thing that thou haſt promiſed and ſealed up to al that ſeeke thee, even blot out all mine of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences out of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and for my ſinnes and iniquities, O
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:847:64"/>Lord remember them no more. Be not wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of making theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, though thou ſeeme to thy ſelfe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive none anſwer to them, but fly conſtantly, and runne boldly to the throne of grace, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine mercy to helpe in time of need. If thy ſoule be vexed with new feares, confirme thou it with new prayers, and reſolve, if thou muſt be damned to be damned praying, and if thou muſt needs periſh, to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with a prayer in thy mouth, then thou canſt
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:847:64"/>not bee damned, then thou canſt not periſh. Call upon God in the day of thy trouble, make thy prayers to him in the flouds of great waters, and ſure they ſhall not come neere thee, for he will fullfill his promiſe, and will grant thee all that thou beggeſt in the name of his Sonne. Thus have you two helpes to comfort, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and meditation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§ 2.</head>
                  <p>The third followes, and that is conference.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:847:65"/>Make thy caſe knowne to others of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for wiſdome lies not all in one breſt, ſo that any one man ſhould bee able for himſelfe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all Satans crafty cavills, eſpecially the weake Chriſtian cannot, therefore muſt he ſhew his caſe, and crave coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; <hi>David</hi> could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelfe, <hi>Bathſheba</hi> could not. Wherefore devoure not thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes all alone, but aske advice, ſeeke abroad for comfort, and make an happy uſe of the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and communion of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:847:65"/>Saints. More eaſily can the divell over reach one then many, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate therefore thy griefes and feares, to ſome or other of Gods faithfull people or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Now is the time of hearkening to the counſell of Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> who bids us, <hi>Confeſſe our faults one to another,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">James 5.16.</note> 
                     <hi>and pray one for another that you may be healed,</hi> when men that are tormented in ſpirit, ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bee ſtopped by ſhame or feare, from opening their wounds, they multiply their own
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:847:66"/>miſeries, and increaſe the flames by ſtifling them. Do not ſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any longer, but make manifeſt thy ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and acknowledge thy ſinnes to ſome or other comforter. A man in a deſperate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe will runne to the Chyrurgion. Bee ſure thou haſt not commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any ſo grievous ſins, but ſome or other of Gods children have committed as bad. Bee ſure that no temptation ceaſeth upon thee, ſo foule and hideous, but the ſame or as bad, hath
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:847:66"/>beene found before in ſome or other of the Saints. J ſay therefore againe, make haſte to ſeeke advice, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thine whole ſoule freely and fully to him whom thou takeſt for thy Phyſitian, and leave nothing, no nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uttered that doth trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee; and reſolve to beleeve rather the words of him that ſeekes to comfort thee, then thine owne ſtrong fancies, and Satans lying cavills a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee. It is evident that a ſound man can eaſily doe that for a ſick
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:847:67"/>man, which hee by no meanes is able to doe for himſelfe in the time of his ſickneſſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe the ſicke ſend for the whole, and the whole come to the ſicke, and even ſo muſt the ſick and comfortleſſe ſoule doe likewiſe, onely doe this ſpeedily, and put not off till thou beeſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy overwhelmed with griefes. As a bone out of joynt, that is too long afore it bee ſet, is farre more hardly reſtored to his place, and is ever ready to be ſlipping out againe: ſo a diſtreſſed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:847:67"/>ſoule that defers to crave counſell, is much more hardly comforted, and doth much more eaſily fall againe into his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted griefes. Speed is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary therefore in the latter of theſe two caſes as well as the former, and great is the hurt of deferring. If thou haſt carryed thy griefes in ſilence long, that that is paſt cannot be remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thou muſt bee ſure it will bee harder and longer afore thou canſt be helped. But if thou beeſt one that now begins to faint, let nor
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:847:68"/>Satan hinder thee from revealing thy caſe, as he will endeavour. Two eyes ſee more then one, and one man alone is eaſily couſened. Shame, ſhame, carnall ſhame hinders many a ſoule from inward comfort; he is aſhamed to tell to others what he findes in himſelfe, as not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all men labour of the ſame diſeaſe of originall ſinne, which is an aptneſſe to every ſinne. If a man have a foule diſeaſe and bee aſhamed to ſhew it, either hee muſt bee the better
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:847:68"/>skilled in Surgery him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or elſe he dies for it, ſo it is for ſinnes. Make ſpeed therefore to look abroad for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, if thou finde not thy ſelfe ablt to deale with thine owne feares and objections.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>Doe this alſo plainely and fully, without any reſervation, ſticke not at any thing that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles thee, but cleere thy minde fully, and wholy, and be not like a childe that holdeth out the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:847:69"/>wrong finger, and will not bee knowne where his worſt paine is. If need be, thou maiſt tie thy Phyſitian to ſecrecy, by the ſtrongeſt bond of an oath, but be not thou in any one thing ſecret or reſerved, chiefely conceale not that ſinne ſinnes or temptations that doe moſt perplexe thee, or any one aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating circuemſtance of them. All labour is loſt till this be done. Till the thorne be pulled out, that cauſeth ſwelling, the ſwelling will not be aſſwaged. The anſwering
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:847:69"/>of all other objections will availe nothing for thy comfort unleſſe this be anſwered. Let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing make thee hold backe any of thy griefes, more then ſtay too long before thou begin to crave helpe. Feare not, ſqueame not to lay open the worſt of thy ſores, let the very iſſue and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie bee ſeene that ſhould be healed. A man ſhall but bungle in the cure that is not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed of the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And as ſick men doe, ſo doe thou; they beleeve their tender ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:847:70"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:847:70"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:847:71"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:847:71"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:847:72"/>then their own eyes or conceits: for ſicke men are exceeding apt to miſtake things out of their bodily diſtemper, and ſo are alſo troubled and diſtempered hearts. Gods words alone can bee the ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, mans may and muſt bee the inſtrument of comfort, that by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man, wee may bee helped to beleeve in God. As a man muſt hope above hope, ſo hee muſt beleeve above beleefe. He muſt captivate his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to his comforter that ſeeles to a comforter,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:847:72"/>and ſay, what hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes for mee out of Gods Word, I will cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, though I cannot feele it to be ſo, and will rely more on his judgement then mine owne. And why ſhould not a wiſe and godly Miniſter bee rather credited, then a lying and malitious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a diſtracted and diſquieted heart? The ſicke mans pallate dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſweete things to be ſower, his dimned eyes can ſee no light at noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide, finding this he cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits thoſe about him, that have better diſpoſed
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:847:73"/>ſences, and judges of things, not as himſelfe thinketh, but as others tell. In this vertuous credulouſneſſe, muſt bee the ſicke ſoules firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of comfort, and he that will thus betake himſelfe to counſell, ſhall finde that in the multitude of counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, there will bee peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p>And ſo much alſo for the third meanes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. I will conclude with the fourth and laſt, namely the right infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:847:73"/>of our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that we may bee able to anſwer ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections as are brought againſt the remiſſion of our ſinnes, and whereby the divell and the fleſh would have us conclude, but the concluſion is falſe, that our ſinnes neither bee, nor ſhall be pardoned. The cheefe of theſe I will ſet downe in order, with their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers ſo well as I am able.</p>
                  <p>But before I ſpeake of them, I will ſhew you what be the onely true arguments to proove
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:847:74"/>that a mans ſinnes bee not, nor (whileſt hee ſo continues) can be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the not feeling of ſinne to bee a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the not confeſſing of ſin plainely to God, and in caſes needfull to man alſo.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to leave it.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for pardon in Chriſt, and in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
                  <p>Theſe foure do infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly prove, that a mans ſinnes are not pardoned,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:847:74"/>neither ſhall bee, ſo long as hee doth remaine in that caſe. But if theſe foure things be done, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That ſinne bee felt with anguiſh and griefe of heart. 2. That it be plainely confeſſed to God and man, in caſe needfull and of offence given. 3. That a man have ſtedfaſtly reſolved to leave it. 4. That he ſeeke and cry for pardon in Chriſt, and in him onely, none other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that can be alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt the pardon of ſinne is of any ſorce. Now I will ſet downe
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:847:75"/>the chiefe objections, and ſhew their invalidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They are drawne likely from foure heads. 1. The greatneſſe of ones ſinnes. 2. The defects of his graces. 3. His owne feelings. And laſtly, his horrible temptations.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§ 5.</head>
                  <p>From greatneſſe of ſinne there are three grand objections. Firſt then, the newly humbled ſinner, looketh backe upon his life paſt, and finding his out-ſtrayings
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:847:75"/>ſo many and ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, and withall, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering for how long a ſpace, with how much hardneſſe and obſtinacy, and againſt how many reproofes and checks, he continued to wallow in them, is ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that there is no poſſibility of pardon. This reaſon muſt be thus framed, Hee that hath committed many and foule offences, perſiſted long in them, with much willfullneſſe, and againſt many meanes, is ſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardoned, and ſhall not be pardoned. But alaſſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:847:76"/>alaſſe, ſo have I done as mine affrighted conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth now beare witneſſe againſt mee: Therefore J neither am nor ſhall bee pardoned. To the which the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, that the firſt propoſition of the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon which the whole is built, is moſt apparantly falſe. There is no Text of Scripture that doth ſay ſo, nor can it bee confirmed by any part of the Word of God, therefore as a falſe ſuggeſtion of the divell or of the guilty heart, it muſt be utterly denied.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:847:76"/>Yea the Scripture doth plainely declare the quite contrary, and doth make it moſt evident, that thoſe in whom all the things mentioned in that propoſition, have beene manifeſtly found, have yet beene pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or might have beene. For did not <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> continue a moſt willfull tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour in moſt grievous kindes, and that againſt many admonitions of Prophets ſent unto him immediately from God, and that ſo that he ſlew and murdered theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:847:77"/>and that alſo, ſo long, till he was caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the darke dungeon and laden with chaines of irons: Yet even then was he accepted, upon his humble confeſſions, and ſupplications: Yea did not <hi>Paul</hi> proceed in perſecuting with great fury, and after that the Lord had ſent his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to worke many ſtrange miracles, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme him with the reſt of the Jews that Jeſus was the Lord, yet went on to blaſpheme that holy Name, and impriſon them that confeſſed it,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:847:77"/>and that all the time from Chriſts reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, till the houre that the Lord did meete him in the way and knocke him downe to the ground: and yet did not God pardon him, and ſet forth him for an example of his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering to chiefe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. It muſt therefore be acknowledged for a certaine truth, that how hainous ſo ever amans ſinnes have beene, how long ſo ever hee have hardened himſelfe in them, how many offers of grace ſo ever he have
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:847:78"/>refuſed, how many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions ſo ever hee have heglected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, yet if hee now doe turne unto the Lord, he ſhall bee accepted. So ſaith <hi>Ieremy,</hi> Chap. 26.13. <hi>Therefore now amend your waies, and your workes, and heare the voice of the Lord your God, that the Lord may repent him of the plague that hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt you.</hi> God had ſent many Prophets, many yeares together, riſing early, and ſending them, at this time alſo he had ſent <hi>Ieremy</hi> with
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:847:78"/>the ſame meſſage againe, and now inſteed of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, they laid hands upon, and were ready to kill him, yet even now he tells them, that if now they would turne, the Lord would repent of he evill. Whatſoever therefore is gone and paſt, if in the preſent time thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, lament, confeſſe amend, thou ſhalt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given. Sinne may ſo harden the finners heart, that he cannot repent, it cannot ſo harden Gods heart againſt him, that if he repent, the Lord will
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:847:79"/>not pardon him. O then beleeve not the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divell. Hee telleth thee, thy ſinnes are ſo many and ſo vile, that they cannot bee forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Lord tells, as obſtinate and as grievous ſinners as ever were, that if they now turne, hee will repent him of the evill, and conſequently they ſhall be pardoned, wilt thou not give credit to God rather then to the divell? This is the firſt doubt taken from ſinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:847:79"/>
                  <head>§ 6.</head>
                  <p>An other and a ſorer followes. Ah I, ſince the time that I thought my ſelfe called and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, have yet againe ruſhed into groſſe and grievous ſinnes, and that alſo willingly and upon deliberation, and what ſhall I doe then, ſure I was but an hypocrite, and ſure J cannot bee pardoned, at leaſt I am not. This reaſon alſo muſt bee caſt into this forme. Whoſoever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his calling and converſion committeth
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:847:80"/>great ſinnes willfully, was ſure but an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, and is not nor can bee pardoned. But ſo have I done, therefore J am but an hypocrite, I am not pardoned nor can be. To this I anſwer againe, that the firſt part of the argument is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly falſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch is alſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. It is falſe that he which hath ſo ſinned after calling was but an hypocrite, and is not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, for this was the verycaſe of <hi>David</hi> whoſe example wee now are handling. Did not hee
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:847:80"/>fall in the felfe ſame fort as thou haſt ſaid, and yet hee was no hypocrite, but he was pardoned. I demand of the there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Haſt thou renewed thy confeſſions nad thy ſorrowes, and thy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of amendment ſince thy fall, and art thou returned to a forme, purpoſe and endeavour of walking before the Lord in uprightneſſe. If thou haſt, then I aſſure thee by warrant of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> example, that thou waſt ſincere before, and that thou art pardoned. If thou haſt not, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:847:81"/>thee now, in Gods name, ſettle about theſe things, &amp; apply thy ſelfe ſeriouſly to renew thy repentance, and to turne againe to God, and thou ſhalt be pardoned. So is the ſecond doubt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered taken from great ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>§ 7.</head>
                  <p>The third followes, and that is worſe then both the former. Ah I have made long defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the covenant of grace, and revolted, backſlided, apoſtated from the waies of God, and in my backſliding
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:847:81"/>veine have runne into, I know not how many and how grievous offences. Since I found ſome good things working in my ſoule, and had for a great ſpace and with great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, continued to walke in the paths of piety. I have againe broken forth and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued a long time in my wandrings, without any care of returning, and therefore now I feare that my caſe is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and that J have committed the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſinne. This ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument muſt bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:847:82"/>caſt into this forme, whoſoever hath beene guilty of long and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous defections and backſlidings, hath his ſinnes unpardoned, and hath committed the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable treſpaſſe, nor can be pardoned. Now ſo I have done, as mine owne heart is too ſure a witneſſe againſt mee: Therefore I neither am nor can bee pardoned. Mine anſwer to this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that the former. The firſt part of it muſt bee denied, as being evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe and againſt the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:847:82"/>Word of God. For <hi>David</hi> in my Text did thus backſlide in ſome degree, but <hi>Salomon</hi> (whoſe birth is here mentioned, and who is here graced with the name <hi>Iedidiah,</hi> becauſe the Lord, not alone did but alſo would love him) did make even ſuch an Apoſtacy to the very full and yet hee recovered himſelfe by repentance, hee was upright before, and hee was pardoned. For hath not the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Iſrael to heale her backſlidings? Tell
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:847:83"/>me then, fince thy back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding, haſt thou not recovered, and with much ſhame and remorſe craved pardon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to doe or labours to doe thy firſt workes. If not, thou art not the man I ſeeke to comfort, unleſſe thou ſhalt now addreſſe thy ſelfe to this reconverſion, as I may ſo terme it. If yea, why then know that thy caſe is good enough, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe that is healed doth never kill, but to thee appertaine the promiſes made to backſliding Iſrael. And whereas
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:847:83"/>thou ſayeſt, my ſinne is ſure that unpardonable ſinne. Underſtand that the Scripture never cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth any ſin unpardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Some ſinnes indeed are never pardoned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the committer thereof doth never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; but that a ſinne repented of ſhould bee uncapeable of pardon, it is more then the Word of God doth ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirme: but if there bee any ſuch ſinne, this ſinne of thine cannot bee that ſinne. For he that wholy falleth away, after ſome degrees of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:847:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:847:84"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:847:85"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:847:85"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:847:86"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:847:86"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:847:87"/>grace received, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that he ſhould renew him againe by repentance, but thou doſt againe renew thy ſelfe by repentance, for thou confeſſeſt, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteſt thy turning aſide, and returneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to crave pardon. Let thine heart returne a true anſwer; doſt thou not finde it aking, and relenting for thine Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtafie, longing, deſirous to come on againe, and carefull to ſeeke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for former decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings? if ſo, then art thou renewed by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:847:87"/>and therefore didſt not wholy fall away. If backſlidings ſhall breed in any man, either utter hardneſſe, or utter deſpaire, ſo that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one is not ſorry for them, or will not ſeeke forgiveneſſe of them, that is a ſore ſigne of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter relapſing, but thou doſt come backe againe to the Lord, falling out with thy ſelfe, for falling of from him, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting downe thy ſelfe before him, above and againſt all hope, doſt crave mercy of him. I am certaine therefore
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:847:88"/>that thy caſe is good, and thou art or ſhalt bee pardoned. And for this ſo terrible objection of backſliding, let the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet fully ſatisfie thee. For to Iſrael that had plaide the harlot from God and followed many lovers, the Lord ſaith by his Prophet, <hi>Yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto me,</hi> Chap. 3 ver. 1. &amp; ver. 12.<note place="margin">Jer. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Returne ô backeſliding Iſrael, and I will not cauſe mine anger to fall upon thee, for I am mercifull ſaith the Lord, and will not keepe anger for ever, onely acknowledge your iniquity,</hi> and ſo
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:847:88"/>forth, and then after, <hi>Turne ô backſliding chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for I am married unto you, and I will take you, one of a city,</hi> and ſo as it followeth in the Prophet. Loe now the truth of God, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fearefull Apoſtacy thou haſt made, if thou returne and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, here is promiſe of acceptance, and this very turning, ſhewes that thou haſt not committed that never-to-be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſin, for that offence is therefore onely never pardoned, becauſe the man that hath runne into
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:847:89"/>it, will never returne, either out of hardneſſe, or deſpaire, or both.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§ 1.</head>
                  <p>ANd theſe objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ariſe from the quality of ſinnes committed, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after calling. An other troope ariſe, from thoſe many wants and defects which the ſoule doth finde in it ſelfe.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:847:89"/>And firſt the ſoule findes fault with it ſelfe for want of repentance, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning thus againſt it ſelfe. Alas I have no repentance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am not pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it muſt bee confeſſed for a truth, whoſoever hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented is not pardoned. But why doſt thou ſay I have not repented? To anſwer this doubt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thy ſelfe aright, what repentance is. It is a duty conſiſting of theſe foure parts: 1. Sorrow for ſin. 2. Confeſſion
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:847:90"/>of it to God. 3. Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt calling upon God in the name of Chriſt for pardon and helpe. 4. A firme purpoſe and endeavour of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Conſider, haſt thou not theſe things, doſt thou not performe theſe actions, or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to performe them? If thou doſt, then thou haſt the grace of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as ſure as he is a man that hath a ſoule and body. O but ſaith the fearefull ſoule, I am not ſorry enough for ſins, I do not grieve for them ſo much as I ſhould, nor
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:847:90"/>crave pardon of them ſo earneſtly as I ſhould, nor mend them ſo well as I ſhould. J anſwer, that is very true, But where hath the Lord ſaid, that he which hath not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed theſe duties ſo well as he ſhould, hath not true repentance? This is no where found in Scripture, it is one of thy falſe conceits, and a very falſe conceit it is, tanding to confound the Law, and the Goſpell; for the Law requireth to doe all things perfectly, and rejecteth all works which a man doth not
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:847:91"/>performe ſo well as hee ſhould, but the Goſpell is a doctrine of grace, and accepts endeavours to performe duties, though one fall farre ſhort of that meaſure of duty which he ought to attaine. Doſt not thou ſtrive and endeavour to doe theſe things more and better, and blame thy ſelfe for defects and failings: If ſo, then doſt thou repent as well as thou ſhouldeſt, in the language of the Goſpell. Yea but J doe not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſinne ſo much as others doe, and as the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:847:91"/>Scriptures tell that ſome godly men have done. I anſwer, but haſt thou not heretofore ſome time with plenty of bitter teares, bewailed thine offences, even allmoſt as much as any the Word ſpeaketh of; &amp; if ſo, then underſtand that theſe large and great ſorrowes are not alwaies to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue; There muſt bee a time of drying ſuch flouds of teares from the eyes of the Saints. I anſwer againe, that if thou haſt not lamented as much as ſome of Gods Saints have done
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:847:92"/>in Scripture, yet thou haſt lamented as much as ſome others, Thou readeſt not of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame lamentation in the converſion of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or <hi>Zaccheus,</hi> and <hi>Matthew,</hi> and ſome others. The Word of God hath left us exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſome that have grieved very much, and of others that have not grieved ſo much, if thou haſt not attained to the examples of one of theſe, yet haſt thou fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the other: and againe, I anſwer, that God doth not reject the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:847:92"/>ſorrowes of his people, becauſe they bee not ſo great as thoſe which others attaine. It is no where ſaid in Scripture, that hee repents not which grieveth not as much as others doe or have done. And for the point of grieving for ſin, underſtand that not the quantity is ſo much to be reſpected as the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; if a man grieve ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much, and his griefe carry him not to confeſſe and ſeeke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and grace and help, and diligently to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour amendment, they
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:847:93"/>be nothing worth, and if they doe bring forth theſe effects, they be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, though they bee not very great.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§ 2.</head>
                  <p>Yea but ſaith the heart yet againe, J can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aske pardon earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and heartily, nor at all pray unto God for it with any life or fervency. I anſwer, why wilt thou ſay ſo? That which a man deſireth more then life, and more then all the profits and pleaſures of life, that he deſireth
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:847:93"/>earneſtly and heartily, I trow, or elſe, who can be ſaid to deſire earneſtly? Now tell me, wouldſt thou not rather chooſe to have thy ſinnes par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and thy ſoule healed, then to have long life, great riches, ſtore of pleaſures, and all worldly contents? if this be true, as thou canſt not denie it, then thou doſt earneſtly pray for theſe things, denying that to be found in thee (as in temptation it is uſuall) which any other man may manifeſtly ſee to be in thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:847:94"/>
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>Yea but I want that laſt part of repentance, and that which is the perfection of all, I do not amend, I doe not amend, but J ſtill ſlip into the ſame ſins, and cannot leave them. Why tell me what ſinnes bee they that thou canſt not leave, Is it murder, blaſphemy, whoredome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O no, but I finde deadneſſe, dullneſſe, coldneſſe in prayer, diſtractedneſſe and forgetfullneſſe in hearing, paſſionateneſſe, impatiency, and a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:847:94"/>like faults, ſtill brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king forth in me. J an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, what doſt thou make of God and of his mercy, when thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeſt from hence that thy ſinnes be not pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Is not hee ready to paſſe by ſuch weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in his children and ſervants, as thou canſt eaſily paſſe by in thine. Doth not hee call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Father, doth not he tell us that he knowes that we be but duſt. Doth not the Scripture ſay,<note place="margin">James 3.2</note> 
                     <hi>In many things wee offend all,</hi> and <hi>who can ſay his heart is cleane?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro 20.9.</note> Sure if this
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:847:95"/>were a good argument that ones ſins were not pardoned, no ſins were pardoned to any ſinner. For finde me a man or woman under heaven, that hath not cauſe to complaine thus. Aſſure thy ſelfe therefore that theſe continuall weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are not contrary to remiſſion of ſinnes. Sanctification muſt bee true, elſe the ſoule is not juſtified, but it is not needfull, nay nor in this life poſſible that it ſhould be perfect. And it is true, ſo long as thou continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to confeſſe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:847:95"/>and ſtrive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though thou bee ſtill cumbred with them, elſe would not Saint <hi>Paul</hi> have ſaid, <hi>The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo that yee cannot doe the things that yee would.</hi> Away with this objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therefore, it ſavours of pride, thou wilt not think thou art pardoned, unleſſe thou canſt bring to God ſome ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of goodneſſe, as might ſeeme halfe, or allmoſt to deſerve it. If thou wilt not beleeve thou art pardoned, till
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:847:96"/>thou finde no ſuch faults, thou ſhalt never beleeve thou art pardoned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p>Yea but I feele not alone theſe common im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, but I feele alſo ſome one or other corruption ſo ſtrong and violent in me, that it doth often even againe and againe breake forth, and that alſo too too palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and groſſely. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, But doſt not thou feele in thine heart a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall warring againſt theſe corruptions. Doſt
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:847:96"/>thou not renew thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull confeſſions, and reſolutions of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as often as thou ſinneſt and farre oftner too? Doſt thou not uſually and ordinarily hold faſt thy reſolution not to ſinne, and art over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come alone ſometimes, but commonly keepeſt under the ſinne from pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable breaking forth? Doſt not thou fall ſeldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and with leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and more reluctati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and riſe ſooner out of the ſinne: Yea is it not thy continuall pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be kept againſt it,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:847:97"/>&amp; doſt not thou find that theſe endeavours keepe thee ſo, that thou offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt not by many degrees, ſo much &amp; often, as before thou didſt, &amp; as elſe thou ſhouldſt doe? I anſwer then, that where ſin hath not dominion, there it is healed, and a mans ſoule is truly ſanctified, and himſelfe in the ſtate of grace;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.24.</note> For it is ſaid, <hi>Sin ſhall not have dominion over you, becauſe you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace.</hi> Now it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that where any ſin is thus conſtantly and conſcionably reſiſted &amp; oppoſed with theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:847:97"/>weapons (namely by the conſideration of Gods goodnes in Chriſt, &amp; of his commandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, threats and promiſes in his Word) it is ſubdued, and the dominion there of is broken: Such an one doth mortifie the deeds of the fleſh by the ſpirit, and is in killing them, though they bee not quite ſlaine, that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not that is perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſiſted, oppugned, fought againſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though ſome ſuch corruption be very vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, &amp; do both often and palpably break out, yet it
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:847:98"/>is pardoned, for he doth not love &amp; ſerve ſin that doth thus fight againſt it and reſiſt it. O but J do not repent in truth. J an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, doſt thou thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and lament and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt every ſin, one as well as an other, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God in ſecret? Then ſurely thou repenteſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for no man ſets againſt all ſin, and that before God, but hee doth it in uprightneſſe and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſoule.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>§ 5.</head>
                  <p>Ah but I have no faith, I have no faith, and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:847:98"/>therefore I am not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. I anſwer firſt, thou maiſt have it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after if thou haſt not yet attained it, yea thou ſhalt have it if thou continue to beg it: yea I anſwer againe, this is a falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, thou haſt faith. For he that doth ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the perfect righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, that he concludes, Chriſt can pardon me, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore followes him with continuall ſupplications for pardon, he hath faith, and a good meaſure of faith too. <hi>For how ſhall they call upon him in whom
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:847:99"/>they have not beleeved</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, &amp; our Saviour ſaith to the blind men that confeſſed hee could helpe them, and ran crying after him for helpe, <hi>according to your faith be it vnto you.</hi> Well therefore thou doſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and though thy faith may be weake, yet ſome it is, &amp; that ſo much as ſhall make thee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for weakeneſſe of faith cannot hinder re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſion of ſins, ſeeing the Apoſtles were pardoned, whom yet our Saviour reprooveth, becauſe they were men of little faith.
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:847:99"/>O but all graces are weak and feeble in me, even ſo weake, that I cannot tell whither I have any or none. I anſwer, an infant is a very weake thing, and hath little and feeble limbs, and ſo ſmall uſe of reaſon, that one can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive him to have any at all, and yet he is a man, a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Grace is as little at firſt as naturall life and reaſon in a new borne babe, but if it be true, all is well, then at laſt it ſhall be ſtrong, and true it is, if one find its own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and be made little
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:847:100"/>in his owne eyes becauſe of its littleneſſe, and mourne becauſe it is ſo little, and would faine have it more, and uſe the beſt meanes he can to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it, and by not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo great an increaſe as he deſireth, is not dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to caſt off all meanes, but rather labours to uſe them more and better, that by them it may at laſt attaine its wiſhed confirmation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:847:100"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>§ 1.</head>
                  <p>SO have I anſwered thoſe objectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are taken from our owne defects of graces: now follow more, taken from want of feeling, yea from feeling of great terrors even from God. Firſt, I anſwer to that objection taken from want of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. It may be thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt that thou haſt no feeling: but haſt thou not
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:847:101"/>ſometimes when thou prayeſt earneſtly ſome little kinde of eaſe and refreſhing and hope? if thou haſt, why that is feeling though thou didſt not know it. And I think ſcarce any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an can ſay he hath conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued long to pray, but he hath had ſome ſuch fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Secondly, I anſwer, if thou haſt had yet no feeling, thou maiſt have in due time, for thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt the right way to get it. And againe J anſwer, <hi>David</hi> had as little fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as thou haſt, when he complained,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.82, 83.</note> 
                     <hi>That his eyes
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:847:101"/>failed in waiting for Gods ſalvation, and that he was become like a bottle in the ſmoke.</hi> A man may feele no comfort in remiſſion of his ſins, and yet have his ſins pardoned: for a Chriſtian as J ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, muſt not live by feeling, but by faith, yea he muſt beleeve firſt, and feele after. Sence will deceive in the judging of colours and quantities, how much more in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things that bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſence. Wherefore what concluſion may be duly diducted out of Scripture, that is moſt
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:847:102"/>true and certaine, though a man have no feeling of it, yea though hee feele the contrary was this concluſion, I have my ſins pardoned, or ſhall have, may be diducted out of Scripture, (for ſuch a man as feeleth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but overwhelming griefes) thus. All that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heavy laden come unto Chriſt ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, but Jam heavy laden and come unto Chriſt, therfore I ſhall be refreſhed and find reſt to my ſoule. For he comes to Chriſt heavy laden, that in the ſence of great
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:847:102"/>anguiſh continues to cry and pray, therefore muſt hee labour to ſupport himſelfe with hope, that his caſe ſhall bee good, howſoever it bee for the preſent, and ſo animate himſelfe to continue praying and crying.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>§ 2.</head>
                  <p>Yea but J find my ſelfe even weary of praying, and ready to faint &amp; give over. I anſwer, ſo did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> too, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. when he ſaid his eyes did faile and he was weary of crying, and yet he cried ſtill, and ſo do thou, which ſo long
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:847:103"/>as thou doſt, thou art in none other eſtate then he was, and therfore in a good eſtate, onely ſo that thou wilt be content, as I ſaid to live by faith and not by feeling. Yea but I am not alone void of all peace and comfort, but even filled with feares &amp; terrors. I anſwer ſo was <hi>David</hi> too, in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by name <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.1. where he ſaith, that <hi>the waters were come unto his ſoule and that he ſtuck faſt in the mire.</hi> If any ſay this is meant alone of danger from his outward ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. J anſwer, beleeve
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:847:103"/>that who can, I cannot. <hi>David</hi> was no coward, that the apprehenſion of a meere naturall death ſhould drive him unto ſuch complaints, ſure there was more in it then ſo, his ſoule alſo was well neere overwelmed with temptations &amp; feares of Gods diſpleaſure as well as thine. So was he that made the 77. Pſalme, he ſaith, <hi>my ſoule refuſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> he neither could nor ſcarce would take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, yea complaines, <hi>will the Lord caſt off for ever?</hi> ſhewing that hee had much adoe to keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:847:104"/>from ſinking under deſpaire. So <hi>Heman</hi> the Ezrahite, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. ſaith, ver. 16. <hi>Thy fierce wrath goeth over me, and thy ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors cut me off,</hi> but how behaved he himſelfe in theſe terrors? he cryed unto the Lord, and ſaid, that <hi>in the morning his prayers ſhould prevent him.</hi> I ſay then to thee, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do thy terrors drive thee, from God, or to God? If from God, let them do ſo no more, and thou ſhalt have comfort, if to God, do ſo ſtill, and that will prove thy ſtate good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:847:104"/>
                  <head>§ 3.</head>
                  <p>And ſo are thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections anſwered, that ariſe from feelings. Now the laſt ſort ſpring from Satans temptations. O J am laden and filled with temptations to deſpaire, to hurt my ſelfe, to bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme God, to deny God and his Word, and other moſt execrable things, and J have long continued in this eſtate. J anſwer, Haſt thou not ſins of thine owne to anſwer for, but that thou wilt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo charge thy ſelfe with the divels ſinnes? under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand therefore that this
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:847:105"/>temptation is grounded upon a meere falſe poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that hee who is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued and moleſted with helliſh temptations is not Gods child, nor hath his ſinnes pardoned. And know that if Satan caſt in the moſt vile temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (for hee can caſt in temptations, as it is ſaid, he put it into the heart of <hi>Iud. is</hi> to betray Chriſt) ſo long as thoſe temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be rejected &amp; abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they be not the mans ſins, but his trialls and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions onely. For tell me, was not Chriſt forty daies in the wilderneſſe
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:847:105"/>tempted of the divell? Doubtleſſe in all that ſpace hee purſued him with all the moſt noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome temptations hee could invent, we read in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of three alone, but we may be well aſſured, that they were above 3000. even numberleſſe. It may ſeeme that thoſe three are recorded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were moſt crafty and ſubtill: when the divell had ſpent all his skill &amp; paines before to no purpoſe, he procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to theſe as his laſt &amp; maine aſſaults; for the two former were ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:847:106"/>conveighed, that a man can ſcarce ſee, that Chriſt had ſinned, if hee had yeelded to them, for might not hee as well make bread of ſtones as wine of water? and leape from the temple, as walk on the ſea? But to worke a miracle at the divels ſuggeſtion (either out of doubting becauſe hee ſpake againſt him, or of preſuming becauſe hee ſpake for him) this had beene a fault in Chriſt. And for the laſt it came ſo ſuddenly and violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it would have even carried a man away
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:847:106"/>before he was aware, to give but one bow for ſuch a reward. Now ſure if Chriſt might be thus tempted forty daies, then any Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maybe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tempted as many moneths, as many yeers. Tell me therefore, doſt thou not oppoſe thoſe temptations by the word of God, and when thou canſt too, by prayers, at leaſt by ſecret groanes &amp; inward ſighs? Are they not moſt bitter to thy ſoule, even more untaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then gaule &amp; worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and wouldſt thou not rather then any thing
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:847:107"/>be rid of them? Canſt thou then bee ſo ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of God as to feare that he will impute them to thee, know that they be only thy miſeries not thy ſins, and this will be a good meanes to rid thee of them. For tell me, hadſt thou a child, which ſome wicked fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſhould locke into a roome that he could not get out, and there ſhould tell thy child, thy father is a raſcall, a villaine, a knave, a theefe, a miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, curſe him, wiſh him hanged, wiſh him dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, cut his throat, and
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:847:107"/>the like, but the childs heart and haire riſeth at the hearing of theſe words, he abhors them, &amp; him that utters them, and would if hee could cut out his tongue that uſeth them. What now wouldſt thou thinke of this child? ſpecially if thy ſelfe ſhouldſt have put them both together, meerely to trie how thy child would behave himſelfe in ſuch a caſe, or for ſome other like purpoſe. Surely thou wouldſt not love thy child one jot the worſe; nay rather much more
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:847:108"/>for this triall. Now doe but conceive that God is as juſt &amp; mercifull as thy ſelfe wouldeſt be, for this is thy caſe directly and none other; or think that ſome filthy fellow had ſurprized thy wife in a roome by her ſelfe, and there ſhould ſolicite her with ſhamefull words &amp; geſtures, which ſhee did repell with diſdaine, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out to thy ſelfe that waſt within hearing to come and helpe her, wouldeſt thou account thy wife leſſe honeſt for this? and not rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her honeſty the
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:847:108"/>more for this. Even ſo it is betwixt thy ſelfe and Satan, and therefore ſuch and none other ſhall the Lords ſentence bee of thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>§ 4.</head>
                  <p>Yea but I have yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſome of theſe vile thoughts, I have yeelded to them, and how then ſhall I do? I anſwer, the multitude and violence of them did ſometimes ſo tire thee, and put thee out of breath and ſtrength as it were, that thou couldeſt not give a loud and earneſt, but alone a faint and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:847:109"/>whiſpering, nay, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Satan hath made thee beleeve that thou didſt yeeld, but know that it is one thing to yeeld to a temptation, an other thing to bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied and tyred with it, that a man is not able to make ſuch ſenſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance as he did once. If a ſtrong and ſturdy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, full of lewd deſires, meeting with an honeſt but weak woman, ſhould ſo long wreſtle with her, till ſhe were quite out of breath and could ſcarce ſpeake or ſtirre any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and in that her wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:847:109"/>ſhould uſe ſome unfit geſture to her, were ſhee the leſſe chaſt wife for that, in the cenſure even of the moſt jealous husband? So then, that that thou calleſt yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, was not yeelding, but an inability through faintneſſe, to make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. § 5. But ſay thou had ſtyeelded to ſom evil, even moſt loath ſome for a little time, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired with reſiſting: Haſt thou not now recalled &amp; recanted thine yeelding, doſt not thou now abhor thy ſelfe for yeelding, crave pardon of it, and
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:847:110"/>reſolve never to do it, nor yeeld to it hereafter any more? Sure if ſome var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let ſhould by much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, intice thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, to let him into thine houſe that he might rob thee, or do thee hurt, and after many repulſes at laſt, ſhould bee ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laide by importunity, that he ſhould conſent, &amp; promiſe to do it; but ſo ſoone as ever the fellow was gone, ſhould abhorre it, and refuſe to put it in practiſe, and with teares in his eyes, come tell thee what had paſſed, craving pardon, wouldſt thou not
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:847:110"/>forgive him? wouldſt thou caſt him out of thine houſe? There have been Princes ſo mercifull, that when ſome have beene inveigled to conſpire their death, but after have repented, &amp; of their own accord revealing the conſpiracy, have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their mercy, could and did ſhew them mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and will not God bee more mercifull then ever man was or can be? Bee not therefore diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned becauſe of thy long temptations, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſodaine yeeldan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This the Lord can
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:847:111"/>and will paſſe by, and much more then this.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>§ 6.</head>
                  <p>So have I anſwered the chiefeſt of thoſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and objections which I could meete with, that are uſed to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Saints from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in perſwaſion of the remiſſion of their ſins. It is your part that would be comforted, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue meditating, praying, conferring, labouring to informe your judgement aright in theſe things, which in doing, you ſhall not looſe your labour. He
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:847:111"/>that ſhall come, will come and will not tarry. The night ſhall paſſe, and the day ſhll ariſe: If any ſay, J have long waited for comfort, and finde it not. I anſwer, ſo did <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> as J ſaid above, but reſolve to waite ſtill on Chriſt, and to continue ſtriving for comfort though you perceive Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle good effect for the time, for the more ſlowly it commeth to you at the firſt, the more fully it ſhall abound in you at thelaſt. If faith cannot comfort you, let hope. If you cannot ſay God hath
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:847:112"/>pardoned me, yet ſay J hope he will, and ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine your ſelves. And that hope, which purgeth your hearts, driveth you to prayer, ſets you at de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance with all ſinne, and makes you eſteeme highly of Chriſt, that will ſupport you, and bring grounded and plentifull comfort in the end. Thoſe of you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, therefore, that have throwne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves downe, pulled down their proud hearts, and tumbled their faces in the duſt before the Lord: Irequire them to
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:847:112"/>yeeld unto God the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his mercy, and to Chriſt the glory of his merits, and to goe away comforted, at leaſt reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute to labour for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, with aſſurance that they ſhall have it, for hee that ſaid, will performe it, <hi>Bleſſed bee they that mourne for they, ſhall bee comforted.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
